Finding Aid for A.F.K. Organski Papers 1959-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
A.F.K. Organski Papers
1959-1998
Organski, A.F.K.
Papers of University of Michigan Professor of Political Science and Faculty Member, Institute for Social Research. Contains correspondence, grants and topical files.
9913 Aa 2
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received fro Organski's widow, Patricia Bard, in October 1998. Donor no. 8775.
The collection is open for research.
University of Michigan professor Abramo Firmo Kenneth Organski was a prominent Political Scientist with appointments in the Political Science and Institute for Social Research (ISR) departments. His texts World Politics: Population and World Power (1965), was considered a standard in the field. His success as a researcher earned him the admiration of research foundations and the attention of policy makers at the national level.
Dr. Organski was born in Rome, Italy in 1923. His family emigrated to the United States in 1939 due to anti-Semitic laws introduced by the Mussolini regime. He became a United States citizen in 1944 and served in the Armed Forces in 1943-45. He held a B.A., M.A. and Ph.D. from New York University and after teaching at Brooklyn College in 1952-65 he joined the U-M faculty. Dr. Organski was also a visiting professor at several Universities around the country and the world. In 1969 he became a member of the American Political Science Association. Professional honors include Italy's Cavaliere della Repubblica Italiana and University of Michigan's Distinguished Faculty Achievement award (1983).
A consistent researcher who focused on both creative & quantitative analysis of international political structures, Dr. Organski produced a number of Social Research projects with a view to analyzing the Cold War era power balance from an nonaligned as well as a NATO perspective. In 1981 Dr. Organski became one of the founders of Polycon Corp, which in 1991 became Decision Insights, Inc., a consulting group for government agencies and private corporations. At the time of his death he was the chairman of the board. Dr. Organski died March 5, 1998 in Vail, Colorado.
The collection is divided into three series: Grants (1.1 linear feet), Topical (1.2 linear feet), and Correspondence (.7 linear feet). All relate primarily to Organski's prolific research in the areas of political science, foreign affairs, political demography spanning three decades and dozens of international topics.
Subjects:
Organski, A. F. K., 1923-1998; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Organski, A. F. K., 1923-1998; Haig, Alexander Meigs, 1924-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains primarily research and travel-related communications between Dr. Organski and a group of his colleagues, including collaborators Jacek Kugler and Bruce Bueno de Mesquita. This series represents mainly the period from 1989-1997 with a few items from his early and mid-career years. The focus of the Correspondence Series is communication supporting his research career, with a few personal interactions and discussions about his teaching. For continuity's sake, correspondence related to Department of Defense issues is kept in the Defense subseries of the Topical series.
  - A (Box 1)
  - American Political Science Association, 1987-1993 (Box 1)
  - Barberis, Walter, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Berarducci, Elio, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Bonante, Luigi, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Bueno de Mesquita, Bruce, 1978-1995 (Box 1)
  - Chelliah, Rasa J., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Cimitero Acattolico per Glis Stranieri, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Earhart Foundation, 1979-1994 (Box 1)
  - Emerson, Rupert, 1964 (Box 1)
  - European University Institute, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - F, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Fleming, Robben W., 1968 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation, Incoming, 1973-1989 (Box 1)
  - G, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Germani, Gino, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Barbara Hinckley, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Hoover Institution, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - House, Arthur, 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - International Business Fellows, 1986-1990 (Box 1)
  - International Studies Association, 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - Jacobson, Harold, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
  - Key, V.O., 1955-1960 (Box 1)
  - Kugler, Jacek, 1980-1991 (Box 1)
  - Lamborn, Alan, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Claire Laporte (Box 1)
  - M, 1978-1989 (Box 1)
  - Mauldin, Parker, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
  - McClintock, David, 1971 (Box 1)
  - P, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Rohreke, Heinrich, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Scaife Foundation, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Sedelev, Boris, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Sidjanski, Dusan, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Skala, Barbara Felden, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Solomon, Richard, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ronald Tamman, Ron, 1975-1996 (Box 1)
  - U, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - W, 1994 (Box 1)
- Grants
  The Grants series is the richest part of the collection. In keeping with Professor Organski's own filing system, results of research are included with original grant proposals. In the case of one grant having been submitted to more than one foundation, only the cover materials of the duplicate proposals are retained. This series provides the intellectual basis of the collection: from his early career to his tenure as full professor, Dr. Organski saw the heightening of the Cold War to the fall of Communism, nine presidential administrations, and the maturing of the United States as a "superpower". His research provides a reflection on the national identity as well as the primary concerns of foreign policy as it evolved year by year.
  - Center For International Peace & Security, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Comparative Political Studies in Latin America, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Earhart Foundation, General Matters, 1974-1994 (Box 1)
  - Effective Population as a Source of International Power, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Effective Population in International Politics, 1971 (Box 1)
  - End of Hegemony: Says Who!, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Estimating Outcomes and Consequences of Interstate Wars, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Pluralism and National Integration, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Extending Relative Capacity Measures to Centralized Economies, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Capability to Absorb/Utilize Technology, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Influences of Macro-Political Changes on Fertility, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Measuring the Political Capacity of Communist Systems, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous/Untitled, 1974-1990 (Box 2)
  - Political and Demographic Transitions, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Political Behavior Study, not dated (Box 2)
  - Political Development, not dated (Box 2)
  - Political Dynamics and Vital Rates, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Political Factors and Policies to Reduce Fertility, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Population Grant, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Population Research Proposal, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Power Transition, A: Retrospective and Prospective Evaluation, 19870 (Box 2)
  - Program of Research on National Estimates, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Program of Research on National Estimates II, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Program of Research on National Estimates-Capabilities, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Program on Peace and Security in a Changing World, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Public Support and the Capacity to Govern, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Relationship Between Public Support and Governmental Capacity, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Research and Training in Population and Political Change, no date (Box 2)
  - Research and Training in the Field of Political Demography, 1974; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Training and Studies in Population Planning, 1966 (Box 2)
- Topical
  Research Materials not connected to any particular proposal or grant are included in Topical under the sub-series Research Papers. For a partial overview of the titles and amounts of the grants from 1965-1990, please see the List of Grants folder in the Topical series. Also of note in the Topical series is the subseries titled Defense, which provides insights into the relationship between social research and the formation of public policy decisions.
  - Budget, General, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Course Materials
    - Political Science 160, 1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Political Science 450, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Political Science 498, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Political Science 650, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Political Science 760, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Decolonization Data, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Defense
    - ARPA/DARPA Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Collaboration Between University of Michigan and Department of Defense, 1985; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Computer Systems Management Inc., 1979 (Box 3)
    - Crisis Management Program, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Department of Defense, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Department of State, not dated (Box 3)
    - Foreign Aid, not dated (Box 3)
    - Judith Daly Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 3)
    - NATO, 1969-1983; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Office of Naval Research (ONR), 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Policy Proposal, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Steven J. Andriole, 1978-1978 (Box 3)
  - Filing System of AFKO (memo about), 1995 (Box 3)
  - List of Grants, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Methodology For Predicting Government Performance, not dated (Box 3)
  - North Vietnamese Economy, AFK Speech About, October 11, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Photograph: AFKO and Alexander Haig, undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph: AFKO with 2 unidentified men, undated (Box 3)
  - Population Commission Testimony, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Population Foundation, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Reviews & Readers, 1961-1990 (Box 3)
  - Research Papers
    - Chiapas Crisis, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Fascism and Modernization, 1969 (Box 3)
    - International Relations Revisited, not dated (Box 3)
    - Italian Elite Study Project, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Method to Limit the Use of the Double Veto (Box 3)
    - Outcome of the Coming Negotiations of the Future Status of Jerusalem: A Strategic Analysis and Forecast, The, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Political Challenge and Economic Risk in the, 1980s; 1964 (Box 3)
    - Population Policy for the United States, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Reflections on SDI: Deterrence, Defense and the Nation State, not dated (Box 3)
    - Tug of War Over The Status of Jerusalem: Leaders, Strategies and Outcomes, The, undated (Box 3)
  - Sesquicentennial of U-M, Symposium, September 26-28, 1967 (Box 3)
  - South African Institute of International Affairs, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
  - Stages of Political Development, Japanese Edition, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Symposia, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Nuclear Weapons Cost Study, not dated (Box 3)
  - University Consortium on National Security, 1992-1993 (Box 3)